Guide to the Roger Hargrave Scrapbooks ALBA.245
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Roger Hargrave Scrapbooks
1873-1984
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hargrave, Roger, 1911-1980
ALBA.245
1 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Roger Hargrave served as a volunteer first-aid man in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade during the Spanish Civil War. He repatriated to the U.S. after suffering shrapnel wounds, returning to his studies at the University of Iowa and later pursuing concurrent careers in teaching, Minnesota Democratic-Farmer-Labor (DFL) politics, and law. The collection is comprised of three scrapbooks; all are of a personal and biographical nature, containing materials ranging from news clippings, personal and professional correspondence, and photographs to personal memorabilia, genealogies, resumes, and certificates. Subjects represented include Hargrave’s involvement in the Civilian Conservation Corps during the Depression, his service in the Spanish Civil War and continued connections with fellow veterans, his education, participation in amateur boxing, careers in teaching, law, and politics, his term as Master of the Euclid Masonic Lodge, his espousal of local causes such as pollution control in Duluth, MN, and his family genealogy. Scrapbook 1, housed separately in the Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers, TAM #236, contains the bulk of Spanish Civil War-related material.
Provenance
Hargrave Scrapbooks 2 and 3 came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. Scrapbook 1 was given to the Tamiment Library at New York University in 2002 by Elizabeth Chestnut and Frederick Akiya as part of the Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers, TAM #236.
Historical/Biographical Note
Roger J. Hargrave was born in Sioux Township, Clay County, Iowa to parents Wallace and Sadie Hargrave on April 22, 1911. His fraternal grandparents James Joseph and Jane Hargrave were pioneer homesteaders in Clay County and Roger himself maintained close ties to the state throughout his young adult life. He attended the local Sioux Township grade school and graduated from Gillett Grove High School, Gillett, Iowa in 1928. Beginning in October 1933, Hargrave served for two years in company no. 1750 of the Civilian Conservation Corp to help his family through the Depression. Prior to this, Hargrave had dropped out of the State University of Iowa due to lack of funds, but returned and graduated with a B.S. in 1936. As an undergraduate, Hargrave engaged in amateur boxing, winning several championships that helped finance some of his college expenses. He also became involved in student activism, especially in the Iowa Branch of the American Student Union, during his last year.
In 1937, Hargrave decided to volunteer for the Spanish Civil War on the side of the Republic. Along with his roommate, Milton Felsen, Hargrave sailed to Paris in March, making a journey to Paris, southern France, the Riviera, and then back to Paris, where the two men enlisted at the office of the American Medical Bureau. Hargrave and his roommate were assigned to an ambulance train under Dr. Randall Sollenberger in Albacete, Spain, the latter as the driver and the former dispensing first aid. In June, Hargrave moved to the Jarama front. After an exploding shell killed Sollenberger, Hargrave was then transferred to Dr. Mark Strass’s medical staff. In July, he was transferred to the Brunete front with the George Washington Battalion. There, he suffered shrapnel wounds and was sent to a hospital in Madrid, where he convalesced for four months. Hargrave spent an additional several months in rest homes in Southern Spain and Barcelona, where he met author Ernest Hemingway and pivotal figure in the Indian independence movement Jawaharlal Nehru, about whom Hargrave would later write his PhD dissertation.
After his repatriation to the States, Hargrave returned to his studies at Iowa State, earning a PhD in Political Science and International Law in 1944. For three years, Hargrave taught political science and international law at the University of Iowa, Bucknell University, and Duluth Teacher’s College.
In 1946, while in Duluth, Minnesota, Hargrave became active in the local Democratic-Farmer-Labor (DFL) Party and served on John A. Blatnik’s campaign committee for Congress. He went on to serve for eight years as Congressman Blatnik’s legislative aide. While working in Washington, Hargrave completed a law degree from National University School of Law, graduating as valedictorian of his class in 1953.
In 1954, upon admittance to the Minnesota Bar, Hargrave returned to Duluth to practice law. He remained politically active locally. He served as DFL Chairman of the 59th Legislative District, campaign chairman of Senator Francis “Frenchy” La Bosse, and a member of the Minnesota “McGovern for President” committee in 1972. Additionally, Hargrave served on the Rudy Perpich Committee for Governor and Lieutenant Governor. He also espoused the local pollution control movement, speaking vocally in local papers against practices of Duluth steel and cement plants and submitting statements before the Minnesota Pollution Control Agency.
He died on June 27, 1980, survived by his wife Anne Gerlovich Hargrave, who compiled the three Hargrave scrapbooks. Anne, daughter of a Socialist father, became active in her union, Textile Workers Local 4, while working at the Klearflax Linen Rug factory in West Duluth. She was also active in the Duluth and Minnesota CIO Councils, serving on the Executive Board of the Minnesota CIO in 1942. She and Roger married in 1960.
Sources: North, Joseph. “Iowa Farmer,” in Men in the Ranks: The Story of 12 Americans in Spain. New York: Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1939.
Arrangement
Scrapbooks are arranged in rough chronological order.
Arranged in rough chronological order within each series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
A file containing biographical information can be found in the Irving Weissman Papers, ALBA #165
ALBA Vertical Files
Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers, TAM #236
Milton Felsen Papers, ALBA #233
Separated Materials
The first in the collection of three scrapbooks resides in the Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers, TAM #236. The scrapbook was given to Mr. Akiya, whose family later donated it to the Tamiment Library as part of his papers.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of three scrapbooks arranged in roughly chronological order, with materials relating to specific moments in Hargrave’s life generally grouped together. The bulk of the material in the collection dates from the 1930s to the 1970s, with the oldest material being photographs of various Hargrave ancestors. All three scrapbooks are of a personal and biographical nature, containing materials ranging from news clippings, personal and professional correspondence, and photographs to personal memorabilia, genealogies, resumes, and certificates. Subjects represented include Hargrave's involvement in the Civilian Conservation Corps during the Depression, his service in the Spanish Civil War and continued connections with fellow veterans, his education, participation in amateur boxing, careers in teaching, law, and politics, his term as Master of the Euclid Masonic Lodge, his espousal of local causes such as pollution control in Duluth, MN, and his family genealogy.
Spanish Civil War-related material constitutes about a third of the contents in Scrapbook 1. These materials include news clippings and photographs of Hargrave and other Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans he befriended. Other Civil War-related materials include personal memorabilia, copies of The Volunteer (organ of the VALB), and medical documentation for treatment of a war-inflicted leg injury. A few additional Spanish Civil War-related news clippings, (informal) veteran reunion photographs, and personal correspondence can be found in Scrapbook 2 and 3. More detailed content description of scrapbooks follows in the container list.
Note that the contents of each scrapbook are organized by type, not by physical order within the scrapbook.
Certificates.; Résumés (personnel records); Memorabilia.; Personal papers.; Articles.; Biography files.; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; Madrid (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Causes.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Periodicals.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Portraits.; Barcelona (Spain); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Sources.; Jarama River Valley (Spain); Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Clippings files.; Duluth (Minn.); Clay County (Iowa) |x History.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Albacete (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Hargrave, Anne Gerlovich; Holburn, Harry; Hargrave, Roger, 1911-1980; Dykstra, Matthew; Blatnik, John A., 1911-1991; Lamb, Leonard; Goff, Irving.; Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.); Groden, Daniel Samuel; Robbins, Al; Felsen, Milt, 1912-2005; Nehru, Jawaharlal, 1889-1964; Perpich, Rudy, 1928-1995; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV -- |v Biography
- Scrapbook 1, 1873-1980
  - Typescripts: RH genealogies; RH U. of Iowa PhD dissertation (1944); The Volunteer (1977, 1980), 1944-1980 (Box 1)
  - Letters re: RH treatment of left leg, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Photographs: RH family and ancestors (1873-1946); RH (1911, 1930s); RH in CCC (1933); Shipboard RH among returning ALB veterans; Dr. Arthur Steindler (orthopedic surgeon); RH and Matthew Dykstra, fellow ALB veteran; Madrid., 1873-1946, Undated (Box 1)
  - News Clippings re: Hargrave family history and Scottish heritage; RH amateur boxing; RH speaking on Spain and fascism; ALB veterans Irving Goff, Harry Holburn, Milton Felsen; artificial limbs., 1930-1980 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia: RH family crest; ALB materials (ambulance guidons, beret, pins, medals), Undated (Box 1)
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1924-1928 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook 2, 1928-1980
  - Typescripts: RH Curriculum Vitae; RH “Speaking Engagements for 1944-1945”; Transcript; RH MA thesis (1942); RH valedictory speech at National U.; RH statement to MN Pollution Control Agency (1967), 1942-1967 (Box 2)
  - Diary Entries re: RH on Blatnik Committee UNESCO trip, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Programs: RH’s Convocation at National U. School of Law, Undated (Box 2)
  - Letters re: RH and teaching career; RH to Blatnik re: legislative aide position; to Blatnik re: resisting pressure to fire RH; RH to AH, 1944-1971 (Box 2)
  - Photographs: RH (1940s); RH vacations; RH and Anne H. honeymoon (1960); RH hunting (1968), 1940-1968 (Box 2)
  - News Clippings re: RH and local IA and MN politics; RH as Blatnik legislative aide; RH public speeches on international politics; RH in Spanish Civil War; RH as attorney in Duluth; RH as master of Euclid Masonic Lodge; RH vs. U.S. Steel Corp’s Duluth plant pollution, 1944-1980 (Box 2)
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1928-1954 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook 3, 1965-1980
  - Typescripts: RH speech re: legal profession; RH memo “State of Roger’s Health”; eulogy written by RH; Remarks at RH’s memorial service, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlet: “40th Anniversary Tribute to the Veterans of ALB”, Undated (Box 3)
  - Flyer: DFL “Vote Perpich for Lt. Governor”, Undated (Box 3)
  - Letters re: RH in local politics; Blatnik to RH; Rudy Perpich to RH; Ronnie McGovern to RH; La Comision de Homenaje a Las Brigadas Internacionales to RH re: donating to homage to brigadiers; to RH re: tour of Spain designed to coincide with homage; Felsens to RH and AH; to AH re: condolences for RH’s death, 1970-1980 (Box 3)
  - Photographs: RH (1980); RH hunting trip (1968); RH, Milton Felson, Mark Straus, Al Robbins, Leonard Lamb, Dan Grodin ALB reunion (1975); family reunion (1977); RH world travels (1965-1980) (Box 3)
  - News Clippings re: Euclid Masonic Lodge (1968); RH in local politics; AH’s scrapbooking (1984), 1968-1984 (Box 3)
  - Death certificate, 1980 (Box 3)